<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section id='repositories' xreflabel='repositories'>
  <title>Repositories</title>

<para>
CentOS Studio creates YUM package repositories. YUM is an application used to
manage updates for CentOS and RHEL, similar to Microsoft Update for Windows.
YUM package repositories play a central role in updating client machines. They
play an equally prominent role in client machine installation, as the same
repositories are used for both.
</para>

<para>
YUM repositories are prevalent in Linux software distribution today. They are
used by operating system providers, as well as by major independent software
vendors and hardware providers, including Adobe, HP and Dell.
</para>

<para>
As a platform for system and application deployment, repositories have several key benefits:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Uniform. Repositories can be used to deploy software and configuration
uniformly, independent of the source (OS provider, OEM, ISV, or internal IT).
This consistency reduces overhead, facilitates automation, and eases
integration of components across multiple providers.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Scalable. Package repositories are scalable to meet the needs of a wide range
of deployment scenarios including consumer/OEM, small business, enterprise,
hosted, and even web farm and massively scaled.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Modular. Because package repositories are native to the operating system, most
major enterprise systems management solutions also support them natively. This
allows IT professionals greater flexibility in their operating environments,
without needing to migrate system images and configuration databases.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>


<para>
YUM repositories are in use by some organizations today for deploying internal
systems and applications. Adoption has been limited, however, given learning
curve and overhead. CentOS Studio lowers the bar for IT Professionals by
providing a flexible, automated platform to create and maintain YUM
repositories.
</para>

  <para>
  CentOS Studio creates two types of repositories: <emphasis>system</emphasis>
  and <emphasis>package</emphasis>.
  </para>

  <section>
  <title>System Repositories</title>
  <para>
  System repositories are used to deploy and maintain complete client machines.
  They contain installation images along with all the software and
  configuration (in the form of RPM packages) necessary to perform client
  installation and updates. Clients can be updated against the system
  repository using either traditional or synchronization methods, the latter
  ensuring that client packages are kept in strict compliance with the system
  repository. CentOS Studio provides the YUM Sync Plugin to enable this support.
  </para>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>Package Repositories</title>
  <para>
  Package repositories have two uses. They can serve as input to system
  repositories. They can also be used for deploying applications to unmanaged
  client machines, such as consumer desktops. Package repositories do not
  contain installation images. Neither generally do they contain packages from
  the base operating system, as these are assumed to be either previously
  installed on the client, or available through standard operating system
  update methods, i.e. YUM.
  </para>
  </section>

  <para>
  This document will describe creating both system and package repositories.
  </para>

</section>
