<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
  <title><application class="software">SolutionStudio</application> Overview
  </title>

  <para>Automating customization, installation and maintenance of Red Hat 
  Enterprise Linux and CentOS systems today requires costly and complex management
  solutions. <application class="software">SolutionStudio</application> provides
  a simple, standard, reliable alternative. SolutionStudio packages 
  user-specified content into standard operating system deployment bundles, or 
  <emphasis>solutions</emphasis>. System solutions can be used to
  deploy and maintain client machines, physical and virtual, in a wide range of
  IT environments.</para>

  <para>A solution is a set of operating system components,
  applications and configuration, packaged for deployment in a standard format.
  Using SolutionStudio you can create and maintain solutions:</para>

  <para><itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>select an operating system,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>combine it with one or more applications,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>set operating system and application configuration parameters,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>build the solution,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>deploy it to clients using standard tools and methods,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>change components and configuration,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>rebuild the solution and</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>update existing clients using standard update tools.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="solutionstudio_overview.png" />
    </imageobject>

    <caption><para>SolutionStudio Overview</para></caption>
  </mediaobject>

  <para><application class="software">SolutionStudio</application> reads 
  a solution definition, gathers various inputs (operating system, applications, 
  and configuration files), and creates a solution 
  with installation images and a package repository. Using the installation
  images, you can deploy the solution to one or more client machines. You can 
  also update existing clients from the solution package repository.
  </para>

  <para>In summary, SolutionStudio is a production system life cycle manager
  for use in defining, building and maintaining solutions that can
  be easily installed and updated on physical, virtual and cloud machines using
  industry standard deployment and update tools.</para>
</section>
