<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
  <title>Building Distributions</title>

  <para>Running 
  <application class="software">SystemBuilder</application> gathers distribution
  content, processes it, and creates a complete distribution.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="build_overview.png" />
      </imageobject>

      <caption><para>SystemBuilder Build Process</para></caption>
    </mediaobject>

  <section>
  <title>Build Input</title>

  <para><application class="software">SystemBuilder</application> uses three classes of input to create distributions: a base operating system, package repositories, and configuration files and scripts. Distribution content is specified using a <xref linkend="distribution_definition">distribution definition</xref>.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><emphasis role="strong"> Base Operating System.</emphasis> SystemBuilder requires a base operating system distribution as input for creating new distributions. The base operating system is defined at the level of operating system name (Red Hat Enterprise Linux or CentOS), version (5) and architecture (i386 or x86_64). The four base operating systems SystemBuilder supports are RHEL-5-i386, RHEL-5-x86_64, CentOS-5-i386 and CentOS-5-x86_64. Base operating system distributions must include both network installation images and package repositories. Base operating system distribution are covered in more detail under <xref linkend="specifying-repositories" />.</listitem>

  <listitem><emphasis role="strong">Package Repositories.</emphasis> SystemBuilder uses RPM package repositories to locate and download software components for the distribution. SystemBuilder requires at least one package repository, that of the base operating system distribution. A typical distribution definition will specify multiple input repositories, including the base operating system update repository, and repositories made available from other internal and external providers. See <xref linkend="specifying-repositories" /> for more information.</listitem>

  <listitem><emphasis role="strong">Configuration Files and Scripts.</emphasis> The final category of distribution content is user-provided configuration files and scripts. Files are copied, and scripts are executed, during client machine installation and updates. For more information, see <xref linkend="configuring-clients" />.</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>Build Process</title>

  <para><application class="software">SystemBuilder</application> uses information from the <xref linkend="distribution_definition"/> to gather distribution content. It processes this information in three primary ways.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Creates a configuration package.</emphasis> SystemBuilder creates a <xref linkend="configuration-package" /> in RPM format. This package contains configuration files and scripts specified in the distribution definition. It also contains SystemBuilder-generated YUM update configuration. See <xref linkend="updating-client-machines" /> for more information on SystemBuilder-generated YUM configuration.</para>

  <para>During this step, SystemBuilder also creates a <xref linkend="distribution-data-file"/>, if one does not exist, in the same folder as the distribution definition. The file has a <filename>.dat</filename> extension. SystemBuilder uses the data file to track and increment the configuration package release number.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><emphasis role="strong">Assembles a package repository.</emphasis> Using the distribution definition, SystemBuilder compiles a list of required packages. It then resolves package dependencies, downloads packages, adds the configuration package (mentioned in the previous item) and creates a complete, self-contained package repository. The package repository is used during network installations to client machines. It is also used during client machine updates.</listitem>

  <listitem><emphasis role="strong">Customizes network install images.</emphasis> SystemBuilder downloads network installation images from the base operating system and modifies them to include distribution-specific information. By default, SystemBuilder configures the installer program contained within the images to access distribution content from the distribution's <xref linkend="download-location"/>. This allows client machines to be installed over the network without needing to provide the download location manually at installation time. SystemBuilder can also be used to completely automate client installations. See <xref linkend="automating-installations"/> for more information.</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para><application class="software">SystemBuilder</application> stores distribution content, both input and generated, in the cache folder, by default <filename type="directory">/var/cache/systembuilder/</filename>. It reuses information from the cache on subsequent runs, where possible, to improve build performance.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>Build Output</title>

  <para>SystemBuilder outputs a complete distribution, a distribution data file and a log file.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><emphasis role="strong">Distribution.</emphasis> The primary output of the build process is a complete distribution containing distribution-specific network installation images and a package repository. Using network installation images you can deploy the distribution to one or more physical or virtual client machines. See <xref linkend="installing-client-machines" /> for more information. The distribution package repository supports client machine updates using YUM. The section <xref linkend="updating-client-machines" /> provides an overview of SystemBuilder's client machine update features.</listitem>

  <listitem><emphasis role="strong">Distribution Data File.</emphasis> As mentioned above, SystemBuilder creates a <xref linkend="distribution-data-file"/> during the build process. This file is used to track and increment the release number of the configuration package.</listitem>

  <listitem><emphasis role="strong">SystemBuilder Log File.</emphasis> SystemBuilder sends output both to the screen and to a log file, located by default at <filename>/var/log/systembuilder.log.</filename></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  </section>

  <para>In summary, SystemBuilder is a production distribution life cycle manager
  for use in defining, building and maintaining distributions that can
  be easily installed and updated on physical and virtual machines using
  industry standard deployment and update tools.</para>
</section>
