<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
  <title>Glossary of Terms</title>

  <para>These terms are specific to the SolutionStudio environment, not to Linux or
  applications that run on Linux. They are arranged in alphabetical order.</para>

  <para><variablelist>

      <varlistentry id="id" xreflabel="ID">
        <term><emphasis
        role="strong"><varname>$ID</varname></emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The id for a solution. The default value consists of the
          <emphasis>/name</emphasis>, <emphasis>/version</emphasis> and
          <emphasis>/arch</emphasis> child elements of the
          <emphasis>main</emphasis> element in the solution definition in the format
          <varname>$NAME</varname>-<varname>$VERSION</varname>-<varname>$ARCH</varname>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="build-system" xreflabel="build machine">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">build machine</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The server on which <application
          class="software">SolutionStudio</application> is installed.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="client-system" xreflabel="client machine">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">client machine</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The target system on which solution contents are installed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="configuration-package" xreflabel="configuration package">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">configuration package</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>An RPM package created by SolutionStudio during the build process. This package contains the <application class="software">YUM</application> sync plugin, SolutionStudio created YUM configuration, and user-specified configuration files and scripts. The name of the configuration package is in the following format, where $VERSION is taken from the <emphasis>version</emphasis> element in the solution definition and $RELEASE is taken from the <xref linkend="solution-data-file" />.
          </para>

          <para><informalexample>
          <filename>system-config-$VERSION-$RELEASE.noarch.rpm</filename></informalexample>
          </para>

          <para>For example, given a solution with the name "samba-server" and version "5", the first time SolutionStudio creates the solution, the configuration package will be named as follows:</para>

          <para><informalexample>
          <filename>system-config-5-1.noarch.rpm</filename></informalexample>
          </para>

          <para>The release number "1" will be written to the solution data file. When configuration changes in the future, e.g. when files or scripts are added, deleted or modified, SolutionStudio will increment the release number by 1, create a new configuration package (in this case samba-server-config-5-2.noarch.rpm), and store the new release number ("2") in the solution data file. The incremented version number allows installed client machines to determine that a new configuration package is available for download and installation.</para>

          <para>For more information on what the configuration package contains
          and how to customize its contents, see the section on 
          <emphasis>config</emphasis> in the Solution Definition File 
          Reference.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="ddfr" xreflabel="SDFR">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">SDFR</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>"Solution Definition File Reference," the rules of syntax for
          the solution definition.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="solution_definition" xreflabel="solution definition">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">solution definition</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The information SolutionStudio uses to build, configure and store
          a solution. By convention the text file uses the <filename
          class="extension">.definition</filename> extension. The file uses XML
          tagging as defined in the SDFR.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="solution-data-file" xreflabel="solution data file">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">solution data file</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A file SolutionStudio creates to track and increment the release number of the solution's <xref linkend="configuration-package" />. This file is created in the same folder as the solution definition, using the same filename, with a <filename>.dat</filename> file extension. For example, given the full path to a solution definition:</para>

          <para><informalexample>
          <filename>/~/samba-server.definition</filename></informalexample>
          </para>

          <para>SolutionStudio will create the data file as follows:</para>

          <para><informalexample>
          <filename>/~/samba-server.definition.dat</filename></informalexample>
          </para>

          <para>Care should be taken not to delete this file. Doing so will cause the release number of the configuration package to restart at "1". As a result, updated configuration packages will fail to be downloaded and installed during client machine updates.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="download-location" xreflabel="download location">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">download location</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The web location (URL) for downloading solution content. SolutionStudio uses this location during the build process for two purposes, for creating YUM client configuration (included in the <xref linkend="configuration-package"/>), and for customizing network install images. By default the download location is as follows, where $IP_ADDRESS is the address of the build machine, and $ID is the solution id.</para>

          <para><informalexample>
            <filename>http://$IP_ADDRESS/solutions/$ID</filename></informalexample></para>

<para>For example, if the IP Address for the build machine is <filename>192.168.1.5</filename> and the solution id is <emphasis>samba-server-5-i386</emphasis> the download location is as follows:</para>

          <para><informalexample>
              <filename>http://192.168.1.5/solutions/samba-server-5-i386</filename>
            </informalexample></para>

          <para>The download location is configurable using the <emphasis>publish</emphasis> element of the solution definition. See the SDFR for information on the publish element. See also <xref linkend="production-definitions"/> for a discussion on using download locations in a production environment.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="solution-repository" xreflabel="solution repository">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">solution repository</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>RPM package repository created during the solution build
          process. Provides packages for use during client machine installations
          and updates. Can be accessed over the network from the 
          <filename type="directory">os</filename> folder of the 
          <xref linkend="download-location"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="strong">production server</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Within a <application class="software">SolutionStudio</application>
          development - staging - production environment, it serves as the
          download server from which clients retrieve the solution contents
          to install.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="strong">staging server</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The server within a development - staging - production
          environment that uses <application
          class="software">SolutionStudio</application> to build production-ready
          solutions for migration to the production, or
          download, server.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="yum-sync-plugin" xreflabel="YUM Sync Plugin">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">YUM Sync Plugin</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A <application class="software">YUM</application> plugin provided by SolutionStudio that allows synchronizing packages on client machines with packages in the <xref linkend="solution-repository"/>. The plugin is included by default in the <xref linkend="configuration-package" />, which serves as the mechanism for installing it on client machines. The plugin establishes the solution repository as the <emphasis>master repository</emphasis>, disables all non-master repositories, and provides a new argument, <emphasis>sync</emphasis>, to YUM. Help for the <emphasis>sync</emphasis> argument is available on client machines using the <command>yum help</command> command. Running <command>yum sync</command> allows YUM to calculate package additions and removals based on packages available in the solution repository. For more information, see the section on <xref linkend="updating-client-machines"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist></para>
</section>
