<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section id='repositories' xreflabel='repositories'>
  <title>Repositories</title>

  <para>
  Repo Studio creates RPM package repositories. RPM is a package management
  system used by CentOS, Red Hat Enterprise Linux, and others to install, update
  and remove software and configuration on client systems. Packages are 
  discrete units of software and configuration managed by RPM. 
  </para>
  
  <para>
  Repositories are collections of packages, typically located on remote servers
  or CD/DVD media. Repositories are generally organized by the architecture (e.g.
  i386 or x86_64) and version (e.g. 5 or 6) of a base operating system.
  </para>
  
  <para>
  RPM package repositories are prevalent in Linux software distribution today.
  They are used by operating system providers, by software and hardware vendors,
  and by systems administrators.
  </para>
  
  <para>
  Repositories have several key benefits for managing deployment of software and
  configuration:
  </para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <para>
  Uniform. Repositories can be used to deploy software and configuration
  uniformly, independent of the source (OS provider, OEM, ISV, or internal IT).
  This consistency eases integration and facilitate automation.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  <para>
  Scalable. Package repositories are scalable to meet the needs of a wide range
  of deployment scenarios including consumer/OEM, small business, enterprise,
  hosted, and even web farm and massively scaled.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  <para>
  Modular. Because packages describe their relationships and dependencies
  internally, it becomes easy to mix, match, replace, update and remove them to
  create custom repositories talored to a variety of needs.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>


  <para>
  Repo Studio creates two types of repositories: <emphasis>system</emphasis>
  and <emphasis>package</emphasis>.
  </para>

  <section>
  <title>System Repositories</title>
  <para>
  System repositories are used to deploy and maintain complete client machines.
  They contain installation images along with all the software and
  configuration (in the form of RPM packages) necessary to perform client
  installation and updates. Clients can be updated against the system
  repository using either traditional or synchronization methods, the latter
  ensuring that client packages are kept in strict compliance with the system
  repository. Repo Studio provides the YUM Sync Plugin to enable this support.
  </para>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>Package Repositories</title>
  <para>
  Package repositories have two uses. They can serve as input to system
  repositories. They can also be used for deploying applications to unmanaged
  client machines, such as consumer desktops. Package repositories do not
  contain installation images. Neither generally do they contain packages from
  the base operating system, as these are assumed to be either previously
  installed on the client, or available through standard operating system
  update methods, i.e. YUM.
  </para>
  </section>

  <para>
  This document will describe creating both system and package repositories.
  </para>

</section>
