<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
  <title>Updating Repositories</title>

  <para>
  To keep your repository current, you will need to run CentOS Studio on a
  regular basis. Each time CentOS Studio runs, it checks for changes in the
  repository definition or in input data - such as new packages available from
  an input repository - and refreshes the repository as necessary.
  </para>

  <para>
  If CentOS Studio finds updated packages, it refreshes the <xref
  linkend="repository"/> to contain just the current set of packages.
  Specifically, when CentOS Studio determines that packages have changed, it
  calculates the list of packages needed to satisfy repository requirements,
  and then adds and removes packages as necessary to bring the repository into
  conformance with the list. This behavior allows the <xref
  linkend="yum-sync-plugin" /> to rely on packages in the repository as a
  master list of packages to be installed on client machines.
  </para>

  <para>
  To update your repository, you use the same command as you used to initially
  build it, for example:
  </para>

  <para>
  <informalexample><programlisting>
# centosstudio web-server.definition
  </programlisting></informalexample>
  </para>

  <para>
  You can automate repository updates using <command>cron</command>. The
  following example shows a shell script that updates the web-server
  repository.
  </para>

  <para><informalexample>
  <programlisting>
#!/bin/sh
DEF_DIR=/root/definitions
PARAMS="\
  $DEF_DIR/web-server.definition \
  "

for params in $PARAMS; do
  centosstudio $params 
done
  </programlisting>
  </informalexample></para>

  <para>
  You can extend this script to update additional repositories by adding lines
  to the PARAMS variable.  To run the script on a nightly basis, save it to a
  file (e.g.  <filename>nightly_build.sh</filename>), copy the file to the
  <filename>/etc/cron.daily</filename> folder, and make it executable (e.g. by
  using the command <command>chmod +x
  /etc/cron.daily/nightly_build.sh</command>).
  </para>

</section>
