<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
  <title>Building a System</title>

  <para>Now that you have defined your system repository, you use the
  <command>systemstudio</command> command to build it. The basic command validates the 
  system definition syntax, creates the system repository, and records 
  process results. The default level of screen output includes errors, build
  status and file download and creation status. SystemStudio also
  sends this output to the log file, by default 
  <filename>/var/log/systemstudio.log</filename>. If a critical error
  occurs, SystemStudio includes detailed error information in the log file.</para>

  <para>The initial build of a system repository can be time consuming, on the order
  of several minutes to an hour or more. Initial build time depends on a number
  of variables including the location of package repositories (local or remote), 
  network connection speed, the number of packages included in the system repository, 
  and the amount of content that can be reused from the SystemStudio shared 
  cache. Subsequent builds complete in much less time, often 1-2 minutes, 
  depending on the level and type of change since the previous build.</para>

  <para>To run your build, enter the command below:</para>

  <para><informalexample>
      <programlisting>#systemstudio samba-server.definition</programlisting>
    </informalexample></para>

  <para>The output for an initial run details all the steps
  for downloading packages, checking package dependencies and creating
  images. If there are any errors, <application
  class="software">SystemStudio</application> notes those and, in many cases,
  halts the process. See Appendix A for an example of a successful first-build
  output.</para>

  <note>If your system repository uses RHN channels as repositories, SystemStudio may occasionally report errors such as the following while downloading or verifying repository metadata:

  <programlisting>[repos] long int too large to convert to int</programlisting> 

This can happen when SystemStudio receives invalid data from RHN. (Typically this occurs when data is being replicated across RHN servers). The error may be corrected by running SystemStudio again, either immediately or after waiting several minutes.</note>

</section>
