<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="creating-deployment-scripts" xreflabel="Creating Deployment Scripts">
  <title>Creating Deployment Scripts</title>

  <para>The first step is to create common deployment scripts that can be used across installation and update test sessions.</para>

    <para>
    The CentOS Studio model for automated deployment is simple, yet flexible and
    and extensible. Repositories can be deployed in a variety of operating
    environments, for example using virtual machines running on a local host,
    virtual machines running on remote or cloud-based hosts, or physical
    machines managed by enterprise systems management systems.
    </para>
  
    <para>
    To accomplish this flexibility, CentOS Studio allows users to provide
    scripts for completing various deployment and maintenance actions. These
    scripts can be written in any shell scripting language.  By default, CentOS
    Studio executes some scripts on the local build machine and others on the
    client machine using <application class="software">Secure Shell
    (SSH)</application>.
    </para>
  
    <para>
    When CentOS Studio executes a script using SSH, it first copies it to the
    client machine using <application class="software">Secure Copy
    (SCP)</application>. After copying, it then executes the script using SSH
    as the <emphasis>root</emphasis> user. CentOS Studio leaves copied scripts
    on the remote machine to assist with troubleshooting. They can be located
    in the <filename>/var/lib/centosstudio</filename> folder. For
    information on other files CentOS Studio copies to the
    <filename>/root/sysconfig/centosstudio</filename> folder, see the <xref
    linkend="config-rpms"/> element. See also the <emphasis> CentOS Studio User
    Manual</emphasis> for more information on testing and troubleshooting
    solution installation and updates.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    CentOS Studio supports password authentication for SSH connections. It does
    not support public key or host-based authentication.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    Users can disable CentOS Studio's built in SSH execution for any script.
    This allows users to provide support for remote connections and
    authentication using any method desired directly within the user-provided
    script.
    </para>
</section>
