<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="smb" xreflabel="Small Business/IT Consultant"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Small Business/IT Consultant</title>

  <para>
  Small business system deployment is often managed by IT consultants who
  service multiple clients. These consultants work remotely when possible, and
  visit the customer location only as needed.  Using System Studio, IT
  Consultants can perform the tasks of system integration and testing remotely.
  Physical installation, which involves burning a CD/DVD and using it to boot
  the physical machine, can be performed by a tech-savvy individual within the
  small business, or by the IT consultant during an on-site visit.
  </para>

  <para>
  To enable this scenario, the IT Consultant must first establish a web server
  that customers will use to access system repositories. This can be a web
  server at the customer location, a hosted web server, or an
  internet-accessible web server maintained by the IT Consultant. The web
  server can be running on any operating system. The only requirements for the web server are that:
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  customer machines can access it over HTTP or HTTPS,
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  the IT Consultant has file system access to the server, for example via SSH,
  and
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  permissions are set so that only the customer and the consultant have access
  to customer repositories.
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
  For this scenario, we assume that the final production machines (e.g.
  laptops, desktops or servers) will be installed manually via CD/DVD. In small
  environments, manual deployment is often more practical than setting up the
  infrastructure required to support automated deployment. Installation can be
  performed by the IT Consultant or a tech-savvy individual within the small
  business. Maintenance will occur automatically using YUM.
  </para>

  <para>
  We assume for this scenario that production machines are strictly
  managed, specifically that all applications and configuration on the machines
  are controlled by the IT Consultant rather than by end users.  Some users may
  require a greater degree of control over their machines, in which case IT
  consultants can accommodate these users following a strategy similar to that
  described under <xref linkend='consumer'/>.
  </para>

  <para>
  Key aspects of small business system repository definitions include the
  following:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  Use of the <emphasis>config-rpm</emphasis> element to configure clients to
  periodically check the web server for updates. In the example below, this is
  done by creating a config-rpm with the ID <emphasis>yum-sync-cron</emphasis>.
  This config-rpm configures the client to run the <command>yum sync</command>
  command on a daily basis using the <command>cron</command> utility. It does
  this by installing a file named <filename>yum-sync</filename> to the
  <filename>/etc/cron.daily</filename> folder, and setting the file mode to
  executable. 
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  Use of the <emphasis>test-install</emphasis> and
  <emphasis>test-update</emphasis> elements to perform ongoing testing 
  prior to making the repository available for use in the customer environment.
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  Use of the <emphasis>remote-url</emphasis> element within the
  <emphasis>publish</emphasis> element to specify the web server location of
  the production repository. This is the location where customers/consultants
  can access system installation images for creating CD/DVD discs. It is also
  the location where client machines will access updates. In the example below,
  the remote-url is specified as
  <filename>http://www.company.com/repos/system/</filename>.
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  Use of the <emphasis>password</emphasis> element within the
  <emphasis>publish</emphasis> element to specify the root user password for
  the production client. If the same repository will be used to deploy multiple
  clients, the password element can be omitted and a unique, per-machine
  password can be provided manually at install time.
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  Use of the <emphasis>kickstart</emphasis> element within the
  <emphasis>publish</emphasis> element to automate CD/DVD-based system
  installation. If the same repository will be used to deploy multiple client
  machines, the <emphasis>network</emphasis> option should be omitted from the
  kickstart to avoid machine hostname collision. In this case the hostname can
  be provided manually during the CD/DVD installation process.  Also, the
  password option may be omitted and the password provided at install time as
  described above.
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  <para>
  Use of the <emphasis>script</emphasis> element within the
  <emphasis>publish</emphasis> element to automate synchronization of the
  repository from the System Studio build machine to the web server location
  specified by the <emphasis>remote-url</emphasis>. This synchronization will
  only occur if the test-install and test-update processes have completed
  without error.
  </para>

  <para>
  In the example below, this is done by providing a script with the
  <emphasis>id</emphasis> 'sync'. The <emphasis>type</emphasis> attribute for
  the script is set to 'update', which will cause System Studio to run the
  script each time changes occur in repository content. The
  <emphasis>ssh</emphasis> attribute is set to <constant>false</constant>,
  directing System Studio to execute the script on the build machine, rather
  than on a remote client. The script synchronizes the published repository on
  the build machine with the customer-accessible repository specified by
  <emphasis>remote-url</emphasis>.
  </para>

  <para>
  The script assumes that SSH public key authentication has been previously
  configured between the build machine and the remote server. See the
  <emphasis>Deployment Guide</emphasis> for Red Hat Enterprise Linux at the Red
  Hat Documentation website <ulink url='http://docs.redhat.com'/> for
  information on configuring key-based authentication for OpenSSH.
  </para>
  </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
  The following example shows a skeleton definition for a small business system
  repository.
  </para>

  <para>
  <emphasis role='strong'>Small business system repository definition</emphasis>
  </para>
  <informalexample>
  <programlisting>
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?&gt;
&lt;repo xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"&gt;

&lt;main>...&lt;/main>

&lt;repos>...&lt;/repos>

&lt;packages>...&lt;/packages>

&lt;config-rpms>
&lt;config-rpm id='yum-sync-cron'>
&lt;files content='text' destdir='/etc/cron.daily' destname='yum-sync' mode='755'/>
#!/bin/sh
/usr/bin/yum -q -y sync
&lt;/files>
&lt;/config-rpm>
...
&lt;/config-rpms>

&lt;test-install>
&lt;password>test-password&lt;password>
&lt;xi:include href="virt-deploy.xml" xpointer="xpointer(/*/*)"/>
&lt;/test-install>

&lt;test-update>
&lt;password>test-password&lt;password>
&lt;xi:include href="virt-deploy.xml" xpointer="xpointer(/*/*)"/>
&lt;/test-update>

&lt;publish>
&lt;web-url>http://remote.company.com/repos/system/&lt;web-url>

&lt;password>production-password&lt;password>

&lt;kickstart>
<xi:include href="templates/deploy/ks.cfg" parse='text'/>
&lt;/kickstart>

&lt;script id='sync-to-production-server' type='update' ssh='false'>
#!/bin/sh
rsync -a --delete -e ssh \
"/var/www/html/repos/system/%{id}/" \
"user@www.company.com:/var/www/html/repos/system/%{id}"
&lt;/script>
&lt;/publish>

&lt;/repo></programlisting>
  </informalexample>

  <section>
  <title>Deploying Clients Manually</title>

  <para>
  Because <application class="software">System Studio</application> creates
  system repositories in a standard format, clients can be deployed manually
  using traditional tools and methods. For the small business scenario, we will
  discuss installation using CD/DVD boot media. See the <emphasis>Red Hat
  Enterprise Linux Installation Guide</emphasis> and <emphasis>Red Hat
  Enterprise Linux Virtualization Guide</emphasis> for information on
  additional installation methods.
  </para> 

  <section id='cd/dvd-network-installation' 
           xreflabel="CD/DVD Network Installation">
  <title>CD/DVD Network Installation</title>
  
  <para>
  In this method, the consultant/customer will use the network install image
  (<filename>boot.iso</filename>) to create an installation CD or DVD.  The
  image can be found in the <filename>images</filename> folder for the
  repository, e.g. <filename
  class="directory">/var/www/html/repos/system/web-server-6-x86_64/images/</filename>.
  </para>

  <para>
  The first step is to download the <filename>boot.iso</filename> file to a
  local machine, and then use CD writing software to burn it to CD/DVD media.
  Depending on the operating system of the local machine, this may be as simple
  as right clicking the file and choosing "Burn disc image" or "Write to Disk".
  On older Windows operating systems, a separate application may be needed 
  to provide ISO image burning capability.
  </para>

  <para>
  Once CD or DVD disk is created, the next step is to place it into the CD/DVD
  drive of the client to be installed, and restart the machine, directing the
  machine to boot from the CD/DVD device if necessary. The boot process will
  load the installer which will complete the installation, retrieving RPM
  packages over the network from the <xref linkend="repository-url"/>. If the
  hostname and root password are missing from the kickstart file, the installer
  will prompt for them at the beginning of installation. 
  </para>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>CD/DVD Complete Installation</title>
  <para>
  System Studio can also create complete CD/CVD install media. In
  this case, the installer program will retrieve RPM packages directly from the
  CD/DVD media, rather than downloading them over the network. This method is
  convenient for installing clients with limited network connectivity. 
  </para>

  <para>
  To direct System Studio to create complete CD/DVD installation images, add an
  <emphasis>iso</emphasis> element to the repository definition, as follows:
  </para>

  <informalexample>
  <programlisting>
&lt;iso>
&lt;set>DVD&lt;/set>
&lt;/iso></programlisting>
  </informalexample>

  <para>
  See the <xref linkend='rdfr'/> for the complete syntax of the iso element. 
  </para>

  <para>
  After running System Studio again, the iso image (or images) will be
  available from the <filename>iso</filename> folder of the repository, e.g.
  <filename
  class="directory">/var/www/html/repos/system/web-server-6-x86_64/iso/</filename>.
  Burn the resulting image(s) to media, and use them to boot client
  machines as described under <xref linkend='cd/dvd-network-installation'/>
  above.
  </para>

  </section>
</section>
</section>

