<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="config-mgmt" 
         xreflabel="Configuration Management Systems"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Configuration Management Systems</title>

  <para>
  A final scenario supported by CentOS Studio is integration with configuration
  management systems such as Puppet. In this scenario, system administrators use
  CentOS Studio for initial client deployment, and the configuration
  management system for ongoing client maintenance.
  </para>

  <para>
  When writing repository definitions for integration with configuration management systems, you will want to do the following:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  Disable the <xref linkend='yum-sync-plugin'/> using the release-rpm element.
  Disabling the YUM Sync Plugin prevents clients from attempting to remove RPM
  packages installed by the configuration management system, but not included
  in the repository.
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  Add a config-rpm for configuring the configuration management system. This
  RPM will install any client side software and settings needed by the
  configuration management system. 
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  Add test-install and test-update elements to perform ongoing pre-production
  testing. 
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  Add a publish element with a custom kickstart and one or more scripts to
  integrate the repository with a production deployment system. See the
  previous sections for information on integrating CentOS Studio repositories
  within various deployment environments.
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
  <emphasis role='strong'>Example</emphasis>
  </para>

  <para>
  The following example shows a skeleton definition for integrating with a
  configuration management system.
  </para>

  <informalexample>
  <programlisting>
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?&gt;
&lt;repo xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"&gt;

&lt;main>...&lt;/main>

&lt;repos>...&lt;/repos>

&lt;packages>... &lt;/packages>

&lt;release-rpm>
&lt;updates sync='false'/>
&lt;/release-rpm>

&lt;config-rpms>
&lt;config-rpm id='configuration-management-system-config>
&lt;requires>configuration-management-client&lt;/requires>
&lt;script type='post'/>
# script to perform client configuration for the configuration management system
&lt;/script>
&lt;/config-rpm>
&lt;/config-rpms>

&lt;publish>
&lt;kickstart>...&lt;/kickstart>

&lt;script ...>
# script to integrate with production deployment management system
&lt;/script>
&lt;/publish>

&lt;/repo>
  </programlisting>
  </informalexample>
</section>

