<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
  <title>Updating a Distribution</title>

  <para>Using your distribution definition file, there are two methods to change
  a system distribution by adding or removing application packages in 
  conjunction with the <command>yum</command> <option>update</option> command
  option. One method uses the <emphasis>packages</emphasis> element, which 
  addresses the distribution repository only, while the other uses 
  <emphasis>config-rpm</emphasis>, which affects changes within the 
  distribution repository and on the installed client machine.</para>

  <para>Regarding updates, if you add a package to your distribution using
  <emphasis>packages</emphasis> in your
  <filename>samber-server.xml</filename> file, <command>yum</command>
  <option>update</option> will include the package in the distribution
  repository, which is available for installation. If you add a new package
  using <emphasis>config-rpm/requires</emphasis>, <command>yum</command>
  <option>update</option> will include the package in the distribution 
  repository <emphasis role="strong">and</emphasis> install it on the client
  system.</para>

  <para>If you choose to update your distribution by removing a package using
  <emphasis>packages/exclude</emphasis>, <command>yum</command>
  <option>update</option> will remove the package from the distribution
  repository but not from the installed client machine. If you use
  <emphasis>config-rpm/obsoletes</emphasis>, <command>yum</command>
  <option>update</option> will remove the package from the distribution
  repository <emphasis role="strong">and</emphasis> the installed client
  system. </para>

  <para>Remember that the <emphasis>packages</emphasis> element installs package
  groups, while the <emphasis>config-rpm</emphasis> element installs
  packages.</para>

  <para>In the example below, you can include two common system administration
  and network connectivity components: an FTP server and editors. The
  <emphasis>packages</emphasis> element includes the two common groups, which
  will
  be available for installation, while the <emphasis>config-rpm</emphasis>
  installs associated RPMs on the client machine, as well. Insert the following
  two lines within the <emphasis>packages</emphasis> element in your
  <filename>samber-server.xml</filename> file.</para>

  <para><informalexample>
      <programlisting>&lt;group&gt;ftp-server&lt;/group&gt;
&lt;group&gt;editors&lt;/group&gt;</programlisting>
    </informalexample>And within the <emphasis>config-rpm</emphasis> element in
  your <filename>samber-server.xml</filename> file, insert these lines to
  automatically include them on the client machine.</para>

  <para><informalexample>
      <programlisting>&lt;requires&gt;ftp&lt;/requires&gt;
&lt;requires&gt;ftp-server-krb5&lt;/requires&gt;
&lt;requires&gt;jedit&lt;/requires&gt;
&lt;requires&gt;gedit&lt;/requires&gt;
&lt;requires&gt;vim&lt;/requires&gt;</programlisting>
    </informalexample></para>

  <para>In the next section, you will learn how to add scripts and trigger and
  activate them based upon key install and uninstall events of other packages.
  </para>
</section>
