<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
  <title>Glossary of Terms</title>

  <para>These terms are specific to the SystemBuilder environment, not to Linux or
  applications that run on Linux. They are arranged in alphabetical order.</para>

  <para><variablelist>

      <varlistentry id="id" xreflabel="ID">
        <term><emphasis
        role="strong"><varname>$ID</varname></emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The id for a distribution. The default value consists of the
          <emphasis>/name</emphasis>, <emphasis>/version</emphasis> and
          <emphasis>/arch</emphasis> child elements of the
          <emphasis>main</emphasis> element in the distribution definition in the format
          <varname>$NAME</varname>-<varname>$VERSION</varname>-<varname>$ARCH</varname>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="build-system" xreflabel="build machine">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">build machine</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The server on which <application
          class="software">SystemBuilder</application> is installed.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="client-system" xreflabel="client machine">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">client machine</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The target system on which distribution contents are installed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="configuration-package" xreflabel="configuration package">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">configuration package</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>An RPM package created by SystemBuilder during the build process. This package contains the <application class="software">YUM</application> sync plugin, SystemBuilder created update configuration, and user-specified configuration files and scripts. The name of the configuration package is in the following format, where $NAME and $VERSION are taken from the <emphasis>name</emphasis>, and <emphasis>version</emphasis> elements in the distribution definition and $RELEASE is taken from the <xref linkend="distribution-data-file" />.
          </para>

          <para><informalexample>
          <filename>$NAME-config-$VERSION-$RELEASE.noarch.rpm</filename></informalexample>
          </para>

          <para>For example, given a distribution with the name "samba-server" and version "5", the first time SystemBuilder creates the distribution, the configuration package will be named as follows:</para>

          <para><informalexample>
          <filename>samba-server-config-5-1.noarch.rpm</filename></informalexample>
          </para>

          <para>The release number "1" will be written to the distribution data file. When configuration changes in the future, e.g. when files or scripts are added, deleted or modified, SystemBuilder will increment the release number by 1, create a new configuration package (in this case samba-server-config-5-2.noarch.rpm), and store the new release number ("2") in the distribution data file. The incremented version number allows installed client machines to determine that a new configuration package is available for download and installation.</para>

          <para>For more information on what the configuration package contains
          and how to customize its contents, see the section on 
          <emphasis>config</emphasis> in the Distribution Definition File 
          Reference.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="ddfr" xreflabel="DDFR">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">DDFR</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>"Distribution Definition File Reference," the rules of syntax for
          the distribution definition.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="distribution_definition" xreflabel="distribution definition">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">distribution definition</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The information SystemBuilder uses to build, configure and store
          a distribution. By convention the text file uses the <filename
          class="extension">.distribution</filename> extension. The file uses XML
          tagging as defined in the DDFR.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="distribution-data-file" xreflabel="distribution data file">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">distribution data file</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A file SystemBuilder creates to track and increment the release number of the distribution's <xref linkend="configuration-package" />. This file is created in the same folder as the distribution definition, using the same filename, with a <filename>.dat</filename> file extension. For example, given the full path to a distribution definition:</para>

          <para><informalexample>
          <filename>/~/samba-server.distribution</filename></informalexample>
          </para>

          <para>SystemBuilder will create the data file as follows:</para>

          <para><informalexample>
          <filename>/~/samba-server.distribution.dat</filename></informalexample>
          </para>

          <para>Care should be taken not to delete this file. Doing so will cause the release number of the configuration package to restart at "1". As a result, updated configuration packages will fail to be downloaded and installed during client machine updates.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="distribution-url" xreflabel="distribution URL">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">distribution URL</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The web location for downloading distribution content. By default this location is as follows, where $IP_ADDRESS is the address of the build machine, and $ID is the distribution id.</para>

          <para><informalexample>
            <filename>http://$IP_ADDRESS/distributions/$ID</filename></informalexample></para>

<para>For example, if the IP Address for the build machine is <filename>192.168.1.5</filename> and the distribution id is <emphasis>samba-server-5-i386</emphasis> the distribution URL is as follows:</para>

          <para><informalexample>
              <filename>http://192.168.1.5/distributions/samba-server-5-i386</filename>
            </informalexample></para>

          <para>The distribution URL is configurable using the <emphasis>publish</emphasis> element of the distribution definition. More information on specifying the distribution URL is available in Chapter 5 under <xref linkend="download-locations"/></para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="distribution-repository" xreflabel="distribution repository">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">distribution repository</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>RPM package repository created during the distribution build
          process. Provides packages for use during client machine installations
          and updates. Can be accessed over the network from the 
          <filename type="directory">os</filename> folder of the 
          <xref linkend="distribution-url"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="download-server" xreflabel="download server">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">download server</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The machine from which client machines download distribution
          contents. By default, the build machine is also the download server.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="module" xreflabel="module">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">module</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A software function within <application
          class="software">SystemBuilder</application> that executes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="strong">production server</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Within a <application class="software">SystemBuilder</application>
          development - staging - production environment, it serves as the
          download server from which clients retrieve the distribution contents
          to install.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="strong">sandbox</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The development portion of a development - staging -
          production environment for a <application
          class="software">SystemBuilder</application> distribution build
          management system.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="strong">staging server</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The server within a development - staging - production
          environment that uses <application
          class="software">SystemBuilder</application> to build production-ready
          distributions for migration to the production, or
          download, server.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="sync-plugin" xreflabel="sync plugin">
        <term><emphasis role="strong">sync plugin</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A <application class="software">YUM</application> plugin provided by SystemBuilder that allows synchronizing packages on client machines with packages in the <xref linkend="distribution-repository"/>. The plugin is included by default in the <xref linkend="configuration-package" />, which serves as the mechanism for installing it on client machines. The plugin establishes the distribution repository as the <emphasis>master repository</emphasis>, disables all non-master repositories, and provides a new argument, <emphasis>sync</emphasis>, to YUM. Help for the <emphasis>sync</emphasis> argument is available on client machines using the <command>yum help</command> command. Running <command>yum sync</command> allows YUM to calculate package additions and removals based on packages available in the distribution repository. For more information, see the section on <xref linkend="updating-client-machines"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist></para>
</section>
