<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
  <title>Installing a Client Machine</title>

  <para>Deployment to a client machines is the next step. Because 
  <application class="software">SystemBuilder</application> creates
  distributions in a standard operating system format, client machines can be
  deployed using the same tools and methods as used for 
  <application class="software">CentOS</application> and 
  <application class="software">Red Hat Enterprise Linux</application>. See the 
  <emphasis>Red Hat Enterprise Linux 5 Installation Guide</emphasis> for 
  complete information.</para> 

  <para>In the samba-server example, you will use a network install image
  to create an installation CD or DVD. To start the installation, you will boot
  the client machine using the CD/DVD. The installer program contained on the
  CD/DVD will then use the network to download files from the distribution URL
  to complete the installation. To complete this example, you must have
  configured the build machine as a web server, as described in 
  <xref linkend="configuring-a-build-machine"/></para>

  <section>
    <title>Creating boot media</title>

    <para>After <application class="software">SystemBuilder</application>
    completes the build, you  will find your distribution in a folder beneath
    the <filename class="directory">/var/www/html/distributions</filename> 
    default directory on the download server. The folder name will be
    the distribution <varname>$ID</varname>, e.g.
    <filename>samba-server-5-i386</filename>.</para>

    <para>To install to a client machine, you burn a boot image to a separate
    media. For this example, burn the <filename>boot.iso</filename> image 
    (found in the <filename class="directory">/os/images</filename> folder 
    below the <filename class="directory">/distributions/samba-server-5-i386
    </filename> folder, above) to a CD or DVD.</para>

    <para>To burn the image, one option is to run the
    <command>cdrecord</command> command from the <filename
    class="directory">/os/images</filename> folder as illustrated below. Note
    the scanbus number sequence, then record the ISO image onto a CD or DVD
    and label the media, including the number sequence. The number sequence,
    e.g. 1,0,0, may differ from machine to machine.</para>

    <para><informalexample>
        <programlisting># cdrecord -scanbus -dev=ATA
# cdrecord -v -dao dev=ATA:1,0,0 boot.iso</programlisting>
      </informalexample></para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Installing a client machine</title>

    <para>Now you are ready to create your client! The standard procedure is
    to boot the client machine from the CD or DVD. The boot process will start
    the machine, and load an installation program, or <emphasis>installer</emphasis> from the CD or DVD into system
    memory. The installer will complete the installation, retrieving additional content over the network from the <xref linkend="distribution-url"/>. When the installation successfully completes, the client
    system will reboot and display a login prompt. You can check the
    <filename>sys.log</filename> file for installation and boot
    process log information.</para>

    <para>One quick test to make sure the install completed correctly is
    to verify the contents of the <filename>smb.conf</filename>
    installed on the client machine. It should match the one provided in the
    distribution definition.</para>

    <para>Congratulations! You now have a Samba server installed on your
    CentOS 5 client.</para>
  </section>
</section>
