<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
  <title>Tying it All Together</title>

  <para>In summary, there are five steps to creating a successful
  distribution.</para>

  <para>First, you configure the <application
  class="software">SystemBuilder</application> build machine to accommodate the
  size and number of distributions you will build and store concurrently for
  download at any single time. The system should be accessible through your
  local network.
  After configuring the hardware, you can install one of the <application
  class="software">Linux </application>OS versions on which <application
  class="software">SystemBuilder</application> runs.</para>

  <para>Then you define your distribution in the <filename
  class="extension">samber-server.xml</filename> file using XML tags
  defined in the DDFR. Your definition includes several key pieces of
  information:</para>

  <para><itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>the name of the distribution, its version and architecture;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the repositories for the OS and application packages, including
        base install and update mirror locations;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the standard package groups for any applications to include and
        any packages to exclude; and</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>custom system configuration files and required packages
        outside the standard application groups.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

  <para>Once the distribution definition is complete, you log on as the root user
  and execute the command <userinput>systembuilder samber-server.xml</userinput>
  to build the distribution. Output goes to the screen and the default log file.
  The first build may take some time, since <application
  class="software">SystemBuilder</application> needs to do everything the first
  time:</para>

  <para><itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>validate the <filename
        class="extension">samber-server.xml</filename> file,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>locate active repositories,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>resolve package dependencies,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>retrieve the necessary packages,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>retrieve other configuration or user-provided files,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>create the <filename>config.rpm</filename> and
        <filename>release.rpm</filename> files,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>create the <filename>boot.iso</filename> and other required
        images, and</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>store the distribution on the download server.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>Deploying client machines requires three steps. First,
  <application class="software">SystemBuilder</application> will publish the
  distribution image files to the download server location from which the client
  system will obtain its initial installation and subsequent updates. By
  default, the location will be in the web server area on the <application
  class="software">SystemBuilder</application> build machine. Second, you create
  the CD or DVD boot media. Lastly, you install the client machine by inserting
  the disk into the client machine and later verifying that the contents are
  correct.</para>

  <para>Updating your distribution, the final step, can involve simply checking
  for mirror repository updates. Depending upon the changes <application
  class="software">SystemBuilder</application> encounters, systembuilder could
  update the distribution with updated packages. After updating the
  distribution, you will need to run <userinput>yum update</userinput> on the
  client machine to keep the client in synch with the current distribution.</para>

  <para>Another method to update your distribution is actually changing the
  definition, <filename>samber-server.xml</filename> for this scenario. Any
  changes to the three required <emphasis>main</emphasis>
  child elements would constitute creating a brand-new distribution. Save these
  changes to a new filename.</para>

  <para>In the Samba CentOS 5 Server example presented here, what you have
  in the end is a distribution for a Samba server on CentOS 5 for the i386
  architecture. It includes GUI applications as well as a web server,
  administration and printing capabilities. Your custom
  <filename>smb.conf</filename> file provides custom <application
  class="software">Samba</application> configuration instructions. The
  packages come from the repositories at <ulink
  url="http://mirror.centos.org">http://mirror.centos.org</ulink> .</para>

  <para>Now that you have your definition, you can modularize your
  <filename>samber-server.xml</filename> file to reuse its parts and
  version the distribution definition file components to make the build process
  more efficient and traceable. Part II explains this process.</para>
</section>
