<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
  <title>Configuring the SystemBuilder Machine</title>

  <para><application class="software">SystemBuilder</application> is designed to work
  in a networked environment. You can install <application
  class="software">SystemBuilder</application> on a <application
  class="software">Linux</application> system operating with <application
  class="software">Fedora</application> 10, <application
  class="software">CentOS</application> 5 or <application class="software">Red
  Hat Enterprise Linux</application> 5. The OS needs to include an http daemon
  with the ability to host web-accessible appliances for download. If you're
  using <application arch="" class="software">Apache</application>, the httpd
  configuration file directive &lt;Directory&gt; specifies the location of the
  default directory for http files.</para>

  <para>For capacity planning purposes, the machine should have a separate
  logical or physical drive for the <filename
  class="directory">/var</filename> directory. <application
  class="software">SystemBuilder</application> uses the <filename
  class="directory">/var/cache</filename> directory during initial and
  subsequent appliance builds and the <filename
  class="directory">/var/www/html</filename> directory for hosting the
  appliances for distribution. Consequently, the drive space allocated should
  be a minimum of 30GB. Depending upon the number and size of the applications
  included in the appliance, you may need more disk space.</para>

  <para>Disk access is another consideration. Due to the size of the files
  handled, fast disk access is preferable. To accommodate the speed
  requirements, it is best to use hard disk drives with Serial Advanced
  Technology Attachment (SATA) interfaces.</para>

  <para>In addition to the SystemBuilder product, the SystemBuilder build system must have a web
  server installed on it in order to distribute the appliance through the
  network. For instructions on installing SystemBuilder and a web server and verifying
  that SystemBuilder is running correctly, see the "Getting Started Guide" on Rendition
  Software's web site.</para>

  <para>Now you are ready to begin defining your appliance!</para>
</section>
