<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
  <title>Versioning Input Files for an Appliance</title>

  <para>To track and audit any changes to the <application
  class="software">Spin</application> files that are critical to the
  definition, configuration and scripts of an appliance, use a revision
  control system, such as <application
  class="software">Mercurial</application> or <application arch=""
  class="software">Subversion</application>. The Red Hat-based Linux OS' that
  Spin works with by default (<application
  class="software">RHEL</application>, <application
  class="software">CentOS</application> and <application
  class="software">Fedora</application>) all have the revision control system
  <application class="software">Subversion</application>
  (<command>svn</command>) installed as a development server. Subversion
  remains the most popular revision control system. For the type of files and
  distributed nature of Spin, though, the revision control system <application
  class="software">Mercurial</application> (<command>hg</command>) may be a
  better option. Mercurial is fast and distributed. Both
  <command>svn</command> and <command>hg</command> work with secure protocols
  -- ssh and https.</para>

  <para>While everything could be revision controlled, there are some key
  non-image files that should be. Within the <application
  class="software">Spin</application> infrastructure and appliance building
  process, candidates for revision control include configuration files,
  appliance definition files and scripts, i.e. files that contain critical
  textual information that may change over time or are commonly used to define
  aspects of multiple appliances, such as common repositories or network
  configuration.</para>

  <para><itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><filename class="extension">.appliance</filename> files,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><filename>spin.conf</filename>,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>appliance configuration files,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>appliance scripts, and</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><filename class="extension">.appliance</filename> XInclude
        files.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

  <para>If you decide to not use a revision control system, you could rename
  the <filename class="extension">.appliance</filename> file or other key
  files every time you make a change to help you "version" your appliance. You
  can also enter comments in the files. Keep in mind that changing the name of
  the <filename class="extension">.appliance</filename> file does not mean
  <application class="software">Spin</application> will build a new appliance.
  As long as the <varname>$APPLIANCEID</varname> remains the same, the
  appliance remains the same.</para>
</section>
