<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
  <title>Building Repositories</title>

  <para>
  During the build process, <application class="software">Deploy</application> gathers content, processes it, creates a repository, and
  optionally runs scripts to test, deploy or maintain client machines.
  </para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="./images/build_overview.png" />
      </imageobject>

      <caption><para>Deploy Build Process</para></caption>
    </mediaobject>

  <section>
  <title>Input</title>

  <para>
  <application class="software">Deploy</application> uses three classes
  of input: a base operating system repository, additional package
  repositories, and configuration files and scripts.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <para>
  <emphasis role="strong">Base Operating System Repository.</emphasis>
  Deploy requires a CentOS-compatible operating system repository as
  input for creating new repositories. Currently supported operating system
  repositories include CentOS and Red Hat Enterprise Linux, version 6
  for i386 and x86_64 architectures, and RedHat Enterprise Linux version
  7 for x86_64. See <xref
  linkend="specifying-input-repositories" /> for more information.
  </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  <para>
  <emphasis role="strong">Additional Package Repositories.</emphasis> Deploy
  uses RPM package repositories to locate and download additional software
  components for the repository. A typical definition will specify
  multiple additional input repositories, including a operating system update
  repository, and repositories made available from other internal and external
  providers. See <xref linkend="specifying-input-repositories" /> for more
  information.
  </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  <para>
  <emphasis role="strong">Configuration Files and Scripts.</emphasis> The final
  category of repository content is user-provided configuration files and
  scripts.  Files are copied and scripts are executed during client machine
  installation and updates. For more information, see <xref
  linkend="building-rpms" />.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>Process</title>

  <para>
  <application class="software">Deploy</application> uses information
  from the <xref linkend="definition"/> to gather repository
  content. It uses this information to complete three primary steps.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <para>
  <emphasis role="strong">Create repository-specific RPM packages.</emphasis>
  Deploy creates two types of packages, the  <xref
  linkend="release-rpm"/> and optional <xref linkend="config-rpms"/>. The
  release-rpm contains Deploy-generated YUM update configuration.
  Config-rpm packages contain user-provided files and scripts specified in the
  definition. Both are discussed under <xref
  linkend="building-rpms" />.
  </para>

  <para>
  During this step, Deploy also creates a <xref
  linkend="data-file"/>, if one does not exist, in the same folder
  as the definition. The file has a .dat extension. This file is
  used to store Deploy generated input data, such as release numbers for
  generated RPMs, that should be maintained along with the definition.
  </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  <para>
  <emphasis role="strong">Assemble a package repository.</emphasis> Using the
  definition, Deploy compiles a list of required packages. It
  then resolves package dependencies, downloads packages, and creates a
  complete, consistent package repository. The package repository is used
  during network installations to client machines. It is also used during
  client machine updates.
  </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  <para>
  <emphasis role="strong">Customize system installation images
  (optional).</emphasis> For system-type repositories, Deploy downloads
  network installation images from the CentOS-compatible repository and
  modifies them to include repository-specific information. Deploy can
  be used to completely automate client installations. The chapters on <xref
  linkend='testing-system-repos'/> and <xref linkend="deployment-scenarios"/>
  describe this in detail.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
  <application class="software">Deploy</application> stores repository
  content, both input and generated, in the cache folder, by default <filename
  class="directory">/var/cache/deploy/</filename>. It reuses information
  from the cache on subsequent runs, where possible, to improve build
  performance.
  </para>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>Output</title>

  <para>
  Deploy outputs a complete repository, a data file and a log
  file.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <para>
  <emphasis role="strong">Repository.</emphasis> The primary output of the
  build process is a complete YUM package repository containing RPM packages.
  For <emphasis>system</emphasis>-type repositories, the repository also
  contains system installation images. Together, the YUM repository and system
  installation images support the complete range of system and application
  deployment and maintenance scenarios. See the chapters on <xref
  linkend='testing-system-repos'/>, <xref linkend='deployment-scenarios'/> and
  <xref linkend='package-repos'/> for more information.
  </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  <para>
  <emphasis role="strong">Repository Data File.</emphasis> As mentioned above,
  Deploy creates a <xref linkend="data-file"/> during the
  build process. This file is used to track Deploy generated input
  information. 
  </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  <para>
  <emphasis role="strong">Deploy Log File.</emphasis> Deploy
  sends output both to the screen and to a log file, located by default at
  <filename>/var/log/deploy.log.</filename>
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>Test, Deploy and Update</title>

  <para>
  The repository generated by Deploy is used to perform testing,
  deployment and maintenance to client machines. These steps can be performed
  in one of three ways:

  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <para>
  Manually by the user or administrator.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  <para>
  Automatically by Deploy using deployment scripts.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  <para>
  Or, because repositories are in a standard format, automatically by any
  systems management system that can deploy and maintain native CentOS and Red
  Hat Enterprise Linux systems.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
  See the chapters on <xref linkend='testing-system-repos'/>, <xref
  linkend='deployment-scenarios'/> and <xref
  linkend='package-repos'/> for additional information.
  </para>
  </section>

</section>
