<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="working-with-templates">
  <title>Working with Templates</title>

  <para>
  Before you can use Deploy, you must first create a definition describing the
  work you want it to do. Definitions can feel somewhat daunting at first, but
  Deploy includes a number of templates to help with the task. In fact, you 
  will almost never create a definition from scratch. It is much easier to
  copy an existing template and modify.
  </para>

  <para>
  After you install Deploy, you can find the default templates in the
  <filename>/usr/share/deploy/templates</filename> folder. You should not
  modify the templates in this folder, however, as your changes may be 
  overwritten in future updates.
  </para>

  <para>
  Instead, you should copy the templates to a new folder, and direct Deploy to
  look for them in this location. This will allow you to make changes, while 
  still preserving the original files for reference.
  </para>

  <para>
  Here are the steps:
  </para>

  <para>
  1. Create a new templates folder and copy files to it. Substitute the name
  of your folder for the text "/my/templates/folder" below.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
mkdir -p /my/templates/folder
cp -a /usr/share/deploy/templates/* /my/templates/folder
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  2. Add a line to <filename>/etc/deploy/deploy.conf</filename> as shown below:
  </para>

  <programlisting>
&lt;deploy>
&lt;templates-path>/my/templates/folder&lt;/templates-path>
&lt;/deploy>
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  As you are creating definitions, you will often want to tell Deploy to
  include a file, or a portion of a file, from a templates folder. You can do
  this using the <varname>%{templates-dir}</varname> macro. When Deploy sees
  this macro it will look for the specified file in a folder listed in 
  <filename>deploy.conf</filename> (multiple folders can be listed). If it
  cannot find the file, it will then search the default location.
  </para>

  <para>
  You will see the <varname>%{templates-dir}</varname> macro used frequently
  throughout the remainder of this document.
  </para>

</section>
