<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="building-custom-rpms">

  <title>Building Custom Packages</title>

  <para>
  Deploy allows building custom RPMs starting from user-specified
  Source RPMs (SRPMs). SRPMs are a standard mechanism for distributing source
  code in a way that is easy to modify and compile into installation packages
  (RPMs) for different operating system architectures. See the Fedora Project's
  <emphasis>RPM Guide</emphasis> for information on creating and modifying
  Source RPMs.
  </para>

  <para>
  The process Deploy uses to build RPMs from SRPMs includes these steps:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    Obtaining a user-provided SRPM.
    </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
    <para>
    Building RPMs using a default or user-provided template. The template
    specifies the rpmbuild environment as well as scripts to complete the
    actual rpmbuild and verification process.
    </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
    <para>
    Signing the built RPMs.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
    <para>
    Including the built RPMs in the repository.
    </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
  Using the <emphasis>srpmbuild</emphasis> element, you specify individual
  SRPMs to build. For each SRPM, you can specify the following:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    The path to an SRPM file, or
    </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
    <para>
    The name of an SRPM and the path to an SRPM repository where it can
    be located, or
    </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
    <para>
    A script that completes desired actions and finally copies an SRPM to a
    location specified by Deploy. This is useful, for example, for
    creating an SRPM from scratch starting from a Source Code Management
    system, or for patching an existing SRPM.
    </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
    <para>
    Optionally, you can specify a custom template for Deploy to use for
    creating the rpmbuild environment and for building and verifying the RPMs.
    </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
  See the <xref linkend='ddfr'/> for complete information and examples for
  using the <emphasis>srpmbuild</emphasis> element.
  </para>


</section>
