<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
  <title>Using Package Repositories</title>

  <para>
  Now that you have completed, tested and published your package repository,
  you are ready for customers to use it. They can use it with Deploy for
  creating their own package or system repositories.  Or they can install
  packages from your repository manually on existing systems. We will discuss
  each of these scenarios below.
  </para>

  <section>
  <title>With Deploy</title>
  <para>
  Your customers can use Deploy for including content from your
  repository within their own system and package repositories. They can do this
  by including the following elements in their definitions:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <para>
  A <emphasis>repo</emphasis> element pointing to your published
  repository.
  </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  <para>
  <emphasis>Package</emphasis> elements naming packages in your
  repository.
  </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  <para>
  <emphasis>Config-rpm</emphasis> elements reusing and customizing
  configuration templates you have made available in your repository. See
  <xref linkend='using-configuration-templates'/> for more
  information on providing configuration templates for your customers to modify.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>On Existing Systems</title>
  <para>
  Your customers can also install packages from your repository manually on
  existing systems using YUM. To do this, they will need to complete the
  following steps:
  </para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <para>
  Download the <xref linkend='release-rpm'/> from your package repository. You
  can make this easy for your customers by providing them with a full path to
  the release-rpm in your final published repository, e.g.
  <filename>https://repos.mycompany.com://application/application-release-6-1.el6.noarch.rpm</filename>.
  </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  <para>
  Install the release rpm using <application>rpm</application>. You can make
  this easy for your customers by directing them to execute the following
  command as the root user:
  </para>

  <informalexample>
  <programlisting>rpm -Uvh path/to/downloaded/rpm</programlisting>
  </informalexample>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  <para>
  Install packages as desired from your repository using YUM, again as the root user, for example:
  </para>

  <informalexample>
  <programlisting>yum install package1 package2</programlisting>
  </informalexample>
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </section>

</section>
